we want to know your limits ahead of
time so let's say we put you through a
10 week block of exercise could be eight
could be six 12 doesn't matter and we
just collect data we don't make any
changes based on your wearable data
whatsoever we're just running the
program as is like we're not collecting
everything and then we're able to look
at all that information and say okay
when did we notice drops in performance
when did we notice maybe getting sick
more often were there any injuries that
popped up and we'll start to identify
where your personal threshold is
and so we'll start to see hey okay you
know uh this particular line don't cross
this many miles per week when we cross
this many miles per week we start doing
more than that we start getting hurt
more often or or we start getting less
return on our investment from a
performance perspective or mood gets
really worse um soreness gets really
high desire to train gets really really
low something like that you will
actually start to find pretty quickly
where your own individual lines are got
to start with data collection now in the
World of Sports this is a classic
example of things like a pitch count so
in in baseball a 100 pitches is like a
very rough number that starting pitchers
will pay attention to in the Major
League level if you go to the Youth
Sports they actually have very specific
restrictions so in high school they can
only pitch a certain amount of innings
before they have to have certain amount
of days off little leagues you know same
thing and the reason they're doing that
is not actually because they know that
that individual kid will get hurt at
that level but they're able to look back
at enough retroactive data and say hey
roughly we start seeing this sharp
increase of injury once we get past 100
pitches or a sharp reduction in
performance past 100 pitches or
Effectiveness or whatever the metric is
that you care about and so that's what
I'm talking about here imagine having
some sort of information like that about
yourself and so you can start
understanding hey in my next program we
don't want to cross this many
repetitions of squats because over 85%
because when I do that's when we've seen
problems in the past or I don't want to
cross as many miles or whatever the the
metric is for you so tracking some data
to get a better understanding of your
overall load or Readiness can be really
helpful for predicting future negative
outcomes the third major advantage to
this stuff is you will actually now be
able to understand if you've truly
crossed the threshold into overtraining
and whether or not this thing is
actually a chronic issue or you're a
little bit fatigued or tired as I
mentioned there's no official scientific
definition of overtraining but what you
actually care about is are you
overtrained relative to you well if you
don't know what relative to you means
because you don't have this information
in your back catalog then you don't
actually know which means you actually
don't know when it's been resolved or
recovered or fixed so having a baseline
understanding of what's normal for you
allows you to say okay I'm lower than
normal I've been lower than normal for
this long and now we start trying to
climb out of that hole when am I back to
Baseline well without Baseline
information you're not going to know so
even returning from negative
consequences becomes suboptimal we will
cover a lot of options for tracking
throughout this show but actually want
to give you something right now and that
is what I call my MVP or minimal viable
solution something I think most people
could do for free or basically no cost
so start off measure something every day
or most days in three different areas
area one is pick something that is
objective this could be a scale your
body weight it could be a uh HRV marker
or a resting heart rate or a respiratory
rate or CO2 something that is about your
body that is not your perception so
that's your objective marker number two
pick a subjective marker this could be
your mood your desire to train your
energy how well you think you slept last
night anything that is up to your
perception of how you're feeling in the
world then number three is what I call
your most severe performance anchor this
is different for everyone but what is
the one thing that is holding you back
the most that you are aware of what is
the thing you were struggling the most
with what is the one the one thing
you're focusing the most on maybe you're
focusing a lot on your training and you
track your running volume it could be
whatever what is that one major thing
that you're working on that is the
biggest hole in your game uh the thing
that is the most key component to you
getting to the next level or achieving
some sort of progress block whatever it
is you're going after so to summarize
all that again pick one thing that is
objective one that is subjective and one
that is measuring something in your most
severe performance anchor or Focus area
once you've decided on your list the
next thing you're going to do is track
each of those for about 30 days could be
a little bit longer could be a little
bit shorter but at least that I wouldn't
take any action based on any of your
data for those first 30 days what you're
going to want to look for are anything
that lands outside of your normal
average back to that standard deviation
for more than 3 to five days so one day
of a bad mood one day of a high body
weight one day of you know reduced
vertical jump performance not a big deal
what we're looking for are looking back
at your 30-day average getting that
score and then you're tracking after
that 30 days and anytime you see
something that is more than one standard
deviation then you can Google how to
calculate a standard deviation if you
have 30 days of information that's
pretty easy if you come anything outside
of that standard deviation for more than
three consecutive days or say three days
out of four or something like that use
your best judgment then you might want
to consider something is happening we're
not going to make reactions on U
respiratory rate being elevated for one
day we're not going to make reactions on
my sleep being a little bit down too
many things play into these scenarios
and it's really acute fatigue it doesn't
tell us that we're plateauing it doesn't
tell us that we're stalling and it
definitely does not tell us that we're
overtraining
we might be a little bit fatigued but
remember causing adaptation requires
overload so a little bit of fatigue when
we're trying to cause adaptation is
actually what we're looking for so once
we've got that established if we see a
metric that is more than two standard
deviations off for more than a couple of
days then you might take action
immediately you're following the program
and you just start really falling off a
cliff and again as a scientist I'm
actually using a pretty strong
definition which is two standard
deviations off my 30day Norm what I'm
trying to get the point at here is we
don't want to overreact to single days
we want to make sure if it's kind of off
for a number of days three to five days
we're going to pay attention if it's
really off though for more than a couple
of days then we might take action a
little bit before that 5-day window but
probably has to be pretty substantial
decrease in numbers before we're going
to worry about it okay if either of
those scenarios happens that big change
negative change for a couple of days or
a smaller but more sustained change for
a long time then we have to start
digging ourselves out of the hole and we
got a whole episode to talk about how to
do that if you enjoyed this clip you can
watch the full episode by clicking here
[Music]